

#### COMPLEX SYSTEMS RESEARCHER · NETWORK SCIENTIST · PHYSICIST

49 South Huntington Ave. Unit. 205, Boston, MA, USA, 02130

□ (+1) 617-758-9258 | ☑ dina.c.mistry@gmail.com | 🏕 dinacmistry.qithub.io | ☑ dinacmistry | 🛅 dina-mistry78

## Summary\_

Researcher in the Network Science Institute at Northeastern University, with an interdisciplinary background in physics, network science and epidemiological modeling. 5+ years experience modeling complex systems found in the real world and contagion phenomena occurring within them. My interests lie in understanding the underpinnings of complex systems in the real world and developing methods for data driven research in public health and social good.

### Education

**Northeastern University** 

Boston, MA

**Ph.D. IN Physics**Jan. 2014 - Exp. Jan. 2019

Dissertation on Complex Networks & Contagion Phenomena, Advisor: Prof. Alessandro Vespignani

**Northeastern University** 

Boston, MA

M.Sc. IN Physics Sept. 2012 - Jan. 2014

**University of Toronto** 

Toronto, Canada

HON. B.Sc. IN PHYSICS & ASTRONOMY, MINOR IN MATHEMATICS WITH HIGH DISTINCTION

Sept. 2007 - June 2012

Undergraduate thesis on the Axisymmetric Geometry of Saturn's Magnetic Fields, Advisor: Prof. Sabine Stanley

## Skills & Expertise

Programming Python (NumPy, Pandas, scikit-learn, NLTK, Basemap), C/C++, MATLAB, Mathematica, Spark, SQL

Visualization Matplotlib, d3, Gephi

## **Experience**

#### **Northeastern University**

Boston, MA

### GRADUATE RESEARCHER, MOBS LAB | NETWORK SCIENCE INSTITUTE

SYNTHETIC CONTACT NETWORKS

Oct. 2015 - PRESENT

- Developed adaptive algorithms to generate synthetic contact networks from real world census and survey data in multiple large, diverse countries accounting for 46% of the world's population, and integrated them into infectious disease models
- · Supervised graduate students in developing their own algorithms to generate synthetic contact networks
- Implemented MCMC methods and mathematical simulations to infer model parameters and validate against serological data
- Maintenance of database with contact networks for 300 global locations
- Designing a website and Python package to provide the research community with a global database of contact patterns, modeling and visualization tools to implement for research on public health emergencies
- Invited speaker at the 2017 Conference on Complex Systems

#### H1N1 PANDEMIC SCENARIO ANALYSIS

Jan. 2015 - PRESENT

- Characterized global epidemic spreading patterns across different scenarios using commercial airline mobility network data from 3200 transportation hubs, statistical mechanics, information theoretic measures, and unsupervised machine learning algorithms
- · Analyzed data from stochastic micro-simulations of pandemic scenarios originating in 7 different geolocations
- Identified and visualized geospatial and temporal predictability of outbreak patterns from stochastic micro-simulations of pandemics starting in different locations and seasons

#### SPREADING OF ZIKA VIRUS IN THE AMERICAS (WWW.ZIKA-MODEL.ORG)

Jan. 2016 - May. 2017

- Worked to produce a stochastic data driven vector borne model of the 2015-2016 Zika outbreak in real-time; in collaboration with diverse research groups
- Aided in streamlined analysis pipeline of simulation data for time sensitive reports to public health agencies
- Collected, processed, and analyzed epidemiological case report data from Pan-American countries for model calibration

COVER MUSIC NETWORK Sept. - Dec. 2014

- Web scraped a database of musicians and cover songs (whosampled.com) to create a temporal network of connected artists
- · Structured, cleaned, analysis and visualization of network with 70,000+ cover songs and 28,000+ artists spanning over 400 years
- · Presented findings at final course examination for PHYS 5116: Complex Networks (slides can be found here)

- · Implemented agent based models of negotiation on conventions and opinion flipping in temporal social networks
- Explored campaign strategies to reduce the time and critical mass needed to drive populations towards consensus, as well as the hindering effects of community structures (echo chambers)
- · Presented findings to 50 scientists at the 2017 International School and Conference on Network Science

## Advanced Schools & Programs\_

Université Laval Quebec City, Canada

COMPLEX NETWORKS WINTER WORKSHOP

Dec 15 - 22 2018

**University of Washington** 

Seattle, WA

7TH ANNUAL SUMMER INSTITUTE IN STATISTICS AND MODELING IN INFECTIOUS DISEASES

CERTIFICATES OBTAINED IN THE MODULES:

July 5 - 22 2015

- Probability and Statistical Inference
- Stochastic Epidemic Models with Inference
- · Simulation-based Inference for Epidemiological Dynamics
- MCMC I for Infectious Diseases
- MCMC II for Infectious Diseases

### Presentations

#### INVITED TALKS

**Institute for Disease Modeling** Seattle, WA

THE EFFECTS OF COMPLEX NETWORKS ON INFECTIOUS DISEASE SPREADING Sept. 2018

Humanyze Palo Alto, CA EXPLORING THE EFFECTS OF COMPLEX NETWORKS ON CONTAGION PHENOMENA Sept. 2018

**Conference on Complex Systems** Cancun, Mexico

THE INFLUENCE OF CULTURAL AND SOCIETAL DIVERSITY ON EPIDEMIC SPREADING Sept. 2017

#### PROFESSIONAL PRESENTATIONS

#### 3MinuteThesis, GWISE, Snell Library, Northeastern University Boston, MA

DATA-DRIVEN APPROACHES TO INFECTIOUS DISEASE MODELING AND THE ROLE OF HUMAN INTERACTION NETWORKS Oct. 2018

**International Conference on Complex Networks** Boston, MA

A DATA-DRIVEN APPROACH TO INFER SOCIAL CONTACT NETWORKS IN THE CONTEXT OF INFECTIOUS DISEASE

MODELING

Mar. 2018

Grad Research Panel, Snell Library, Northeastern University

Boston, MA DATA-DRIVEN APPROACHES TO STOCHASTIC INFECTIOUS DISEASE MODELING Feb. 2018

International School and Conference on Network Science Indianapolis, IN

COMMITTED ACTIVISTS AND THE RESHAPING OF STATUS-QUO SOCIAL CONSENSUS June 2017

POSTER PRESENTATIONS

### Research, Innovation, and Scholarship Expo, Northeastern University

USING DATA-DRIVEN MODELS TO INFER SOCIAL CONTACT PATTERNS IN THE CONTEXT OF EPIDEMICS

Boston, MA Apr. 2016

### **Publications**

- 5. D. Mistry, A. Pastore y Piontti, M. Litvinova, M. F. C. Gomes, S. A. Haque, K. Mu, X. Xiong, Q. Liu, L. Fumanelli, S. Merler, M. Ajelli, A. Vespignani. A data approach to inferring social contact patterns: the influence of cultural and societal diversity on infectious disease spreading around the world. Manuscript and website in progress.
- 4. D. Mistry, K. Sun, A. Pastore y Piontti, M. F. C. Gomes, L. Rossi, A. Vespignani. Characterizing the global spread of epidemics and their predictability through human mobility networks. Manuscript in progress.
- 3. K. Sun, Q. Zhang, A. Pastore-Piontti, M. Chinazzi, D. Mistry, N. E. Dean, D. P. Rojas, S. Merler, P. Poletti, L. Rossi, M. E. Halloran, I. M. Longini, A. Vespignani. Quantifying the risk of Zika virus local transmission in the continental US during the 2015-2016 ZIKV epidemic. BioMed Central Medicine. 2018. Manuscript accepted for publication. bioRvix link

2. Q. Zhang, K.Sun, M. Chinazzi, A. Pastore-Piontti, N. E. Dean, D. P. Rojas, S. Merler, **D. Mistry**, P. Poletti, L. Rossi, M. Bray, M. E. Halloran, I. M. Longini, A. Vespignani. Spreading of Zika virus in the Americas. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.114. 22.E4334-E4343.2017. **PNAS link** 

1. **D. Mistry** Q. Zhang, N. Perra, A. Baronchelli. Committed activists and the reshaping of status-quo social consensus. Phys. Rev. E.92. 042805. 2015. **APS link** 

# Teaching \_\_\_\_\_

2014	<b>Physics Lab Instructor</b> , U.S. Pathway Program, a summer bridge program for international students	Northeastern University
	from China and Nigera	Wortheastern onliversity
2012-2014	Physics Lab Instructor, Introductory Physics Labs (16 sections), Department of Physics	Northeastern University
2013-2014	Physics Workshop Leader, (6 sections) Department of Physics	Northeastern University
2012	Interactive Learning Sessions Teaching Assistant, Department of Physics	Northeastern University
2011	AST201H1 Teaching Assistant, Department of Astronomy & Astrophysics	University of Toronto

## Service & Leadership \_\_\_\_\_

2018	Women's Summer Retreat organizer, GWISE (Graduate Women in Science and Engineering)	Cambridge, MA
2018	Program Committee member, Art of Networks reception and Society of Young Network	Boston, MA
	Scientists (SYNS) pre-conference event organizer, International Conference on Complex Networks	
2018	Panel member, Graduate School & Research, Dept. of Physics, Northeastern University	Boston, MA
2017	Manuscript subreviewer, PLOS ONE	
2017	Panel member, Diversity and Inclusion Town Hall, College of Science, Northeastern University	Boston, MA
2017	Workshop organizer on professional development, Dept. of Physics, Northeastern University	Boston, MA
2016-2018	Graduate Student Union Dept. Leader, Dept. of Physics, Northeastern University	Boston, MA
2014-2016	Physics Graduate Student Representative, Northeastern University	Boston, MA
2013	TEDx Cambridge Volunteer, TEDx Cambridge	Cambridge, MA
2012	Transit of Venus Outreach Science Volunteer, Dept. of Astronomy & Astrophysics	Toronto, Canada
2011-2012	Vice President of Academic Affairs, Physics & Astronomy Student Union, University of Toronto	Toronto, Canada

### Awards & Honours \_\_\_\_\_

2014 - 2018	<b>Graduate Research Assistantship Award</b> , Department of Physics	Northeastern
		University
2015	Summer Institute in Statistics and Modeling in Infectious Diseases (SISMID) Scholarship, 7th	University of
	Annual Summer Institute	Washington
2012 - 2014	Graduate Teaching Assistantship Award, Department of Physics	Northeastern
		University
2012	Anna & Alex Beverly Memorial Fellowship, for future graduate studies	University of Toronto
2012	Marie Sklodowska-Curie Association Undergraduate Scholarship, for academic excellence in	University of Taranta
	Physics	University of Toronto
2011	<b>Undergraduate Summer Research Award</b> , Highly competitive research assistantship award.	
	Conducted experiments to study the nonlinear growth patterns of stalactites. Advisor: Prof. Stephen	University of Toronto
	Morris.	
2008-2012	Dean's List of Scholars, Faculty of Arts & Science	University of Toronto
2008	C. L. Burton Scholarship for Mathematics and Physics, Faculty of Arts & Science	University of Toronto
2007	Top Scholar's Scholarship, Faculty of Arts & Science	University of Toronto
2007	President's Entrance Scholarship, Faculty of Arts & Science	University of Toronto

## Media

PROJECTING THE SPREAD OF ZIKA The Atlantic, New Scientist, Homeland Security News Wire, WBUR Boston NPR's News Station PHD PROFILE: Canis lupus Graduate Student Newsletter, Northeastern University